Guide to the Brigid Brophy Collection, 1937-1953
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Brigid Brophy collection 1937-1953
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Brophy, Brigid, 1929-1995.
0.6 Linear Feet 10 Items
Brigid Antonia Brophy, Lady Levey (1929-1995), was an English writer of novels, biographies, essays, and other works.
Collection consists of nine volumes of Sigmund Freud's works in English, annotated by Brigid Brophy, who was admittedly influenced by his theories. Also includes an untitled manuscript on telepathy by Brophy, originally inserted in Freud's Collected Papers, Vol. IV.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Brigid Brophy Collection were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2010.
Biographical and Historical Note
"A lifelong crusader for multitudinous causes ranging from writers' rights and animal rights to sexual freedom, women's liberation, and vegetarianism, Brophy produced a varied and extensive body of work. Her best-known novels are The King of a Rainy Country (1956), The Finishing Touch (1963), and In Transit (1969). Admittedly influenced by Sigmund Freud's theories, Ronald Firbank's literary style, and G.B. Shaw's aesthetics, Brophy's writings express unconventional and controversial opinions about modern relations, religious education in schools, sexual psychology, pornography, and gender issues." (Excerpt from Contemporary Literary Criticism, Vol. 105, 1998)
Chronology List
12 June 1929 Born in London, England
1947 Admitted to St. Hugh's College, Oxford University. Left Oxford in 1948.
1953 The Crown Princess and Other Stories, Viking (New York, NY)
1953 Hackenfeller's Ape, Hart-Davis (London)
1954 Married Michael Levey
1956 The King of a Rainy Country, Secker and Warburg (London)
1962 Black Ship to Hell, Harcourt (New York, NY)
1962 Flesh, Secker and Warburg (London)
1963 The Finishing Touch, Secker and Warburg (London)
1964 Mozart the Dramatist: A New View of Mozart, His Operas and His Age, Harcourt (New York, NY)
1964 The Snow Ball, Secker and Warburg (London)
1966 Don't Never Forget: Collected Views and Reviews, Cape (London)
1967 Religious Education in State Schools, pamphlet, Fabian Society (London)
1967 Co-author, with husband Michael Levey, and Charles Osbourne: Fifty Works of English and American Literature We Could Do Without, Rapp and Carroll (London)
1968 Black and White: A Portrait of Aubrey Beardsley, Cape (London)
1969 In Transit: A Heroicycle Novel, Macdonald and Co. (London)
1969 The Rights of Animals, Animal Defence and Anti-Vivisection Society (London)
1972-1982 Co-organizer, Writers' Action Group for Public Lending Right
1978 Palace Without Chairs: A Baroque Novel, Atheneum (New York, NY)
1981 Michael Levey is knighted; Brophy becomes Lady Levey
1983 A Guide to Public Lending Right, Gower (Hampshire, England)
1984 Diagnosed with multiple schlerosis
1987 Baroque 'n' Roll and Other Essays, David and Charles (North Pomfret, VT)
1989 Reads: A Collection of Essays, Cardinal (London)
7 August 1995 Died from multiple schlerosis in Louth, Lincolnshire, England
Collection Overview
Collection contains nine volumes of Sigmund Freud, English translations, published between 1937 and 1953. Included are Volumes I-V of his Collected Papers, as well as Civilization and its Discontents, The Interpretation of Dreams, Inhibitions Symptoms and Anxiety, and Group Psychology and the Analysis of the Ego. All volumes were owned and used by Brigid Brophy, and include her extensive notes on the front flyleaves; some volumes also include her signature or additional annotations in the margins of the text. Brophy's untitled manuscript on telepathy was originally included in Vol. 4 of the Papers, and is now housed in a folder in the box.
Bibliographic description: Nine vols.; portrait frontispiece in the first work; 2 pp. in Vol. II of Papers failed to print; 8vo, original cloth; 3 vols. with dust wrappers; spines darkened, that on Vol. 1 of the Papers frayed; all volumes with extensive notes on the front flyleaves, and occasionally elsewhere, by Brigid Brophy; text with underlinings and a few notes; 3 vols. signed by Brigid Brophy; with, loosely inserted in Vol. IV of the Papers, an untitled manuscript essay on telepathy (or The Uncanny, as Freud has it), 2 1/3 pp, 4to, good.
Publication details: All are The Hogarth Press and the Institute of Psychoanalysis except the second, George Allen & Unwin Ltd.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Brophy, Brigid, 1929-1995
Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939
Psychoanalysis
Women authors -- United Kingdom -- 20th century
Authors, English -- 20th century
English literature -- 20th century -- History and criticism
Influence (Literary, artistic, etc.)
Influence (Psychology)
Contents of Collection
- Collection of Sigmund Freud Texts, 1937-1953, (1 box)
  - Freud, Sigmund. Civilization and its Discontents (London: Hogarth Press and The Institute of Psychoanalysis, 1939). (Box 1)
    Brophy's notes on the front flyleaf.
  - Freud, Sigmund. The Interpretation of Dreams (London: George Allen & Unwin Ltd, 1937). 1945 Reprint.
    Brophy's signature and extensive notes on front flyleaves. Brief annotations in margins throughout.
  - Freud, Sigmund. Inhibitions Symptoms and Anxiety (London: Hogarth Press and The Institute of Psychoanalysis, 1948).
    Brophy's signature and brief notes on front flyleaf.
  - Freud, Sigmund. Group Psychology and the Analysis of the Ego (London: Hogarth Press and The Institute of Psychoanalysis, 1949).
    Brophy's signature and brief notes on front and back flyleaves, as well as annotations in margins of Chapters IX-XI. Long annotations on pp 87, 96.
  - Freud, Sigmund. Collected Papers, Vol. 1 (London: Hogarth Press and The Institute of Psychoanalysis, 1953).
    Brophy's brief notes on front flyleaf.
  - Freud, Sigmund. Collected Papers, Vol. II (London: Hogarth Press and The Institute of Psychoanalysis, 1953).
    Brophy's notes on front flyleaf.
  - Freud, Sigmund. Collected Papers, Vol. III (London: Hogarth Press and The Institute of Psychoanalysis, 1953).
  - Freud, Sigmund. Collected Papers, Vol. IV (London: Hogarth Press and The Institute of Psychoanalysis, 1953).
    Brophy's notes on front flyleaf and brief annotations in margins. Removed to folder: An inserted untitled manuscript essay on telepathy (or The Uncanny).
  - Freud, Sigmund. Collected Papers, Vol. V (London: Hogarth Press and The Institute of Psychoanalysis, 1953).